# César Sosa-Padilla

Curriculum Vitae

### February 2020

	Current Appointments
2019–20 AY	Peter B. Kenen Fellow, Princeton University, Princeton, NJ, USA.
Since 2018 –	Rev. Thomas J. McDonagh, C.S.C. Assistant Professor of Economics, <i>University o Notre Dame</i> , Notre Dame, IN, USA.
Since 2016	Assistant Professor of Economics, University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, IN, USA.
Since 2017	<b>Faculty Fellow</b> , Kellogg Institute for International Studies – University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, IN, USA.
	Previous Appointments
2012 - 2017	<b>Assistant Professor of Economics</b> , <i>McMaster University</i> , Hamilton, ON, Canada. <i>On leave 2016–17</i>
2015 - 2018	Associated Researcher, ADEMU Project.
2011 - 2012	Research Assistant to Prof. Enrique G. Mendoza, University of Maryland, College Park MD, USA.
Summer 2011	Summer Intern, International Monetary Fund, Washington DC, USA, Research Department
2008 - 2011	Research Assistant to Prof. Carmen M. Reinhart, University of Maryland, College Park MD, USA.
Summer 2010	<b>Dissertation Intern</b> , <i>FRB Atlanta, Atlanta GA</i> , USA, Americas Center and Research Department.
Summer 2009	Dissertation Intern, FRB Richmond, Richmond VA, USA, Research Department.
2006 - 2008	Teaching Assistant, University of Maryland, College Park, USA.
2006	Adjunct Professor, Universidad del Norte Santo Tomás de Aquino, Argentina.
2003 - 2005	Teaching Assistant, Universidad Nacional de Tucumán, Argentina.
	Education

- 2012 Ph.D. in Economics, University of Maryland, College Park MD, USA.
- 2008 M.A. in Economics, University of Maryland, College Park MD, USA.
- 2005 Licenciado en Economía, Universidad Nacional de Tucumán, Argentina, cum laude.

#### Research Interests

Primary International Economics and Finance, Macroeconomics.

Secondary Credit Risk, Fiscal Policy, Computational Economics.

#### Honors and Awards

- Peter B. Kenen Fellowship, Princeton University, 2019-2020.
- Rev. Thomas J. McDonagh, C.S.C. Assistant Professorship, College Chair, University of Notre Dame, 2018 - 2021.
- o John Charles Polanyi Prize (Economic Sciences), 2016.
- Hilda Moskowitz Graduate Fellowship, University of Maryland, Spring 2012.
- o Graduate Assistantship, University of Maryland at College Park, 2006 2012.
- 1st escort of Argentinean Flag (Award to the best student of the class), Universidad Nacional de Tucumán, 2005.
- Selected as one of the "Emerging Young Leaders in Latin America" by Fundación Carolina,
   Spain. 2005. Fellowship.

### **Publications**

John Kealey, Pau S. Pujolas, and César Sosa-Padilla. Trade liberalization and firm productivity: Estimation methods matter. *Economic Inquiry*, 57:1272–1283, 2019. [link].

César Sosa-Padilla. Sovereign defaults and banking crises. *Journal of Monetary Economics*, 99:88–105, 2018. [link].

Juan Carlos Hatchondo, Leonardo Martinez, and César Sosa-Padilla. Debt dilution and sovereign default risk. *Journal of Political Economy*, 124:1383–1422, 2016. [link].

Juan Carlos Hatchondo, Leonardo Martinez, and César Sosa-Padilla. Voluntary sovereign debt exchanges. *Journal of Monetary Economics*, 61:32–50, 2014. [link].

César Sosa-Padilla. Firms' financing, contract enforcement, and liability dollarization. *Journal of CENTRUM Cathedra*, 3(1):10–17, 2010. [link].

# Working Papers

- o "Interest Rate Uncertainty and Sovereign Default Risk" (with Alok Johri and Shahed K. Khan). Revise and Resubmit at the Journal of International Economics.
  [link to original submission]
- "Debt, Defaults and Dogma: politics and the dynamics of sovereign debt markets" (with Johnny Cotoc and Alok Johri). [link]
- "Reserve Accumulation, Macroeconomic Stabilization and Sovereign Risk" (with Javier Bianchi). [link to slides]
- "Optimal Bailouts in Banking and Sovereign Crises" (with Sewon Hur and Zeynep Yom).[link to preliminary draft]

### Policy Papers

"Fiscal Rules: Coping with Revenue Volatility in Lesotho and Swaziland" (with J.Honda, F. Im, N. Koliadina, M. Morgan, M. Nose and J. Torres). *IMF African Department WP*.
 [link]

### Work in Progress

- "A Quantitative Theory of the Domestic Share of Sovereign Debt: Equilibrium Repression" (with Yuanhao Niu and Zach Stangebye). In progress.
- o "A Political Inequality Trap" (with Augusto Nieto-Barthaburu). In progress.
- "A Quantitative Analysis of ESBies" (with Juan Carlos Hatchondo and Leonardo Martinez).
   In progress.

## Seminars and Conferences Presentations (including scheduled)

- 2020 FRB Cleveland, Stony Brook University, FRB Minneapolis, FRB Philadelphia, Rutgers University, University of Rochester, International Monetary Fund, Midwest Macroeconomics Conference (Logan, UT).
- 2019 ND-PUC Luksburg Conference on Recent Advances in Macroeconomics (Santiago, Chile), 4th Annual Notre Dame Mini-Conference on International Economics and Finance, Banco Central de la República Argentina, Universidad Nacional de Tucumán, Salento Macro Meetings (Galatina, Lecce, Italy), NBER International Finance and Macroeconomics Fall Meeting (Boston, MA), Princeton University.
- 2018 ADEMU 'Sovereign Debt in the 21st Century' Conference (Toulouse, France), Chicago Workshop on International Economics (FRB Chicago), Tsinghua Workshop in International Finance (Beijing, China), SED Annual Conference (Mexico City, Mexico), Banco Central de Chile, UTDT Annual Conference, Conferencia de Egresados UNT.
- 2017 2nd Annual Notre Dame Mini-Conference on International Economics and Finance, Trinity College Dublin, SED Annual Conference (Edinburgh, Scotland), Conference in Honor of Dr. Víctor Elías (Universidad Nacional de Tucumán), University of Warwick, Queen's University, Carleton University, University of Wisconsin–Madison.
- 2016 FRB Atlanta, University of Notre Dame, George Washington University, Federal Reserve Board of Governors, U.C. Santa Cruz, IDB Research Department, FRB St. Louis, European University Institute, SED Annual Conference (Toulouse, France).
- 2015 World Bank Research Department, European University Institute, Banco Central de Chile, PUC-Chile, Argentine Regional Science Association 5th Annual Meeting (Tucumán, Argentina), PAELLA Workshop (University of Notre Dame), University of Toronto, Université de Montréal, York University, Universidad Nacional de Tucumán (Argentina), RIDGE Sovereign Debt Workshop (UBA, Argentina).
- 2014 Society for Economic Dynamics Annual Conference (Toronto, Canada).
- 2013 Univ. of Western Ontario, Carnegie-Rochester-NYU Conference on Public Policy (NYU Stern), Universidad Torcuato Di Tella (Argentina), Canadian Econ. Assoc. Annual Conference (Montréal, Canada), North-American Summer Meeting of the Econometric Society (USC), Univ. Nacional de Tucumán (Argentina), Di Tella 'XVI Workshop in International Economics and Finance' (Dominican Republic), IMF Institute, Wilfrid Laurier University.

- Bank of England, FRB Atlanta, North Carolina State University, McMaster University, IDB
   Research Department, FGV-EPGE (Brazil), Univ. Nacional de Tucumán (Argentina),
   Canadian Macro Study Group (Montréal), FRB Richmond Conference on Sovereign Debt.
- 2011 Universidad Nacional de Tucumán (Argentina), 17th International Conference on Computing in Economics and Finance (San Francisco, CA), University of Maryland Macro/Int'l Brownbag.
- 2010 Eastern Economic Association Annual Conference (Philadelphia, PA), Royal Economic Society Annual Conference (Guilford, UK), University of Maryland Macro/Int'l Brownbag, FRB Atlanta, Society of Economic Dynamics Annual Conference (Montréal, Canada)
- 2009 FRB Richmond, University of Maryland Macro/Int'l Brownbag, Universidad Nacional de Tucumán (Argentina).

### Discussions

- A. Karantounias, "Greed versus Fear: Optimal Time-Consistent Taxation with Default,"
   Joint Central Bankers' Conference. FRB Atlanta, October 2019.
- M. Gödl, "Disentangling the Eurozone Crisis: A DSGE Perspective," Kellogg Institute Work-in-Progress Meeting. University of Notre Dame, October 2018.
- L. Schiumerini, and D. Steinberg, "The Black Market Blues: The Political Costs of Illicit Currency Markets," *Kellogg Institute Work-in-Progress Meeting*. University of Notre Dame, February 2018.
- o D'Erasmo, P., and E. Mendoza, "Optimal Domestic (and External) Sovereign Default," Annual Atlanta Fed–Emory University International Econ. Workshop. December 2017.
- L. Ohanian, P. Restrepo-Echavarria, and M. Wright, "Bad investments and missed opportunities? Postwar capital flows to Asia and Latin America," 2nd Annual Missouri Macro Workshop. Washington University in St. Louis, March 2017.

# Lifetime Research Funding

- 2019 **Kellogg Institute Grant**, *University of Notre Dame*, Project: "2019 PAELLA Workshop". Amount: USD 3,000
- 2019 Small Henkels Lecture Award, ISLA, University of Notre Dame, Project: "4<sup>th</sup> ND Miniconference on International Economics and Finance".
  Amount: USD 3,000
- 2018 Travel to International Conferences Grant, ISLA, University of Notre Dame. Amount: USD 2,108
- 2018 **Luksburg Foundation Grant**, *Notre Dame International*, Project: "The Notre Dame- PUC Luksburg Conference on Recent Advances in Macroeconomics".

  Amount: USD 12,000
- 2017 **Small Henkels Lecture Award**, *ISLA*, *University of Notre Dame*, Project: " $3^{rd}$  ND Miniconference on International Economics and Finance".

  Amount: USD 4,900
- 2017 **Travel to International Conferences Grant**, *ISLA*, *University of Notre Dame*. Amount: USD 2,107

2017 **Small Henkels Lecture Award**, *ISLA*, *University of Notre Dame*, Project: "ND-TCD Conference on International Finance".

Amount: USD 5,000

2016 – 2018 **Insight Development Grant**, *SSHRC*, Project: "Regulating Capital Flows to Emerging Markets", Co-Pi: Julien Bengui (Univeristé de Montréal).

Amount: CAD 67,955

2015 – 2016 Standard Research and Creative & Performing Arts Grant, ARB - McMaster University, Project: "The Fiscal Costs of Banking Crises under Sovereign Default Risk". Amount: CAD 4,900

2013 – 2015 Insight Development Grant, SSHRC, Project: "Financial Innovation and Inequalities", Co-Pi: Julien Bengui (Univeristé de Montréal).
Amount: CAD 31.600

Summer 2014 **Economics Department Summer RAship Position**, *McMaster University*, Project: "Exporting Status and Productivity: A Nonparametric Redux", Co-Pi: Pau S. Pujolàs (McMaster University).

Amount: CAD 4,500 (plus benefits)

2012 – 2013 Standard Research and Creative & Performing Arts Grant, ARB - McMaster University, Project: "Debt Dilution in Sovereign Borrowing: A Novel Measure and Alternatives to Cope with it".

Amount: CAD 6,998

Summer 2010 Jacob K. Goldhaber Travel Grant, University of Maryland.

Amount: USD 500

2005 – 2006 **CIUNT Young Researchers Start-up Grant**, *Universidad Nacional de Tucumán*, Project: "Inequality in Argentina".

Amount: ARS 6,000

2004 – 2005 **CIUNT Completion of Undergraduate Studies Grant**, *Universidad Nacional de Tu- cumán*, Project: "Topics in International Trade and Technology Adoption".

Amount: ARS 3,600

# Visiting Positions and Consulting

- 2020 Visiting Scholar, Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, Minneapolis MN, USA.
- 2020 Visitor, Federal Reserve Bank of Cleveland, Cleveland OH, USA.
- 2019 Visiting Scholar, Federal Reserve Bank of Philadelphia, Philadelphia PA, USA.
- 2016, 19 Visiting Scholar, Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis, St. Louis MO, USA.
  - 2016 **Visiting Research Fellow**, European University Institute, Florence, Italy.
- 2010, 13, **Visiting Scholar**, *International Monetary Fund*, Washington DC, USA.

15, 20

- 2014 Consultant, World Bank, Washington DC, USA.
- 2013 **Visiting Scholar**, *CIREQ*, *Université de Montréal*, Montréal QC, Canada.

#### Other Professional Duties

Organizer 2014 Canadian Macroeconomics Study Group, 2015 McMaster International Economics Workshop, Annual Notre Dame Mini-Conference on International Economics and Finance (2017-), 2017 IM-TCD-ND Workshop on International Macroeconomics and Capital Flows, PAELLA Workshop at Notre Dame (2017-), ND-PUC Luksburg Conference on Recent Advances in Macroeconomics (2019).

Referee American Economic Review (x3); American Economic Journal - Macroeconomics (x4); Canadian Journal of Economics; Economic Inquiry; Economic Journal; Economics Letters (x2); European Economic Review; International Economic Review (x3); IMF Economic Review; International Finance; Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control (x3); Journal of the European Economic Association (x5); Journal of Development Economics; Journal of International Economics (x3); Journal of Money, Credit, and Banking; Journal of Monetary Economics (x3); North American Journal of Economics and Finance; OeNB (Austrian National Bank) Working Paper Series; Review of Economic Dynamics (x2); Review of Economic Studies (x3).

Reviewer Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRC), Fondo Nacional de Desarrollo Científico y Tecnológico (FONDECYT, Chile)

Departmental Junior Recruiting Committee (Member, 2015-16), Chair Selection Committee (Member, Service (at 2015), Ad-hoc Website Committee (Member, 2014-15), Departmental Representative to McMaster) School of Graduate Studies Theses Defenses (2013-14).

Professional American Economic Association, LACEA, Canadian Economic Association, Econometric Affiliations Society, Royal Economic Society.

Other Maryland Population Research Center, Affiliated Graduate Student (2008-2012); UMD Economics Graduate Student Association, Co-chair (2007-2008); "Becker Center on Chicago Price Theory" (U. of Chicago) Summer Camp 2008.

# Graduate Advising

University of Notre Dame

- o Carlos Rondón Moreno. Committee member. Graduation date: 2019. First job: Central Bank of Chile.
- Yuanhao Niu. Committee member. Expected graduation date: 2021.

McMaster University

- Waheed Olagunju. Committee member. Graduation date: 2016. First job: KAPSARC.
- o John Kealey. Committee member. Graduation date: 2016.
- Sabreena Obaid. Committee member. Graduation date: 2017. First job: Bank of Canada.
- Shahed Khan. Committee member. Graduation date: 2018. First job: York University.

External Member

- o Ricardo Vicente European University Institute. External committee member. Graduation
- Johnny Cotoc McMaster University. External committee member. Expected graduation date: 2020.

# Teaching

### University of Notre Dame

- o ECON 73002 Graduate Macro Workshop. Main Instructor. Grad. level. Spring 2018.
- ECON 70554 International Macro II. Main Instructor. Grad. level.
   Spring 2017, Fall 2018.
- ECON 30020 Intermediate Macro. Main Instructor. Undergrad. level. Falls 2016, 2017, 2018.

### McMaster University

- ECON 752 International Finance. Main Instructor. Grad. level. Winters 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016.
- ECON 724 Macroeconomic Theory II. Main Instructor. Grad. level.
   Winters 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016.
- ECON 3H03 Int'l Monetary Economics. Main Instructor. Undergrad. level. Fall 2012, Winters 2014, 2015, 2016.
- o ECON 3K03 Monetary Economics. Main Instructor. Undergrad. level. Fall 2015.

### University of Maryland

- ECON 325 Intermediate Macroeconomics (for Econ-majors only). Main Instructor.
   Undergrad. level. Summer 2008, Winter 2010.
- ECON 744 International Macroeconomics with Incomplete Markets and Financial Frictions.
   TA. Grad. level. Fall 2011.
- ECON 201 Introductory Macroeconomics. TA. Undergrad. level. Spring 2007, Fall 2007.
- o ECON 200 Introductory Microeconomics. TA. Undergrad. level. Fall 2006.

#### Universidad Nacional de Tucumán (Argentina)

- o Topics in International Economics. *Main Instructor*. Grad. level. 2015.
- o Advanced Macroeconomics. Main Instructor. Grad. level. Summer 2008.
- o Econometrics. TA. Undergrad. level. AYs 2004, 2005.
- Introductory Macroeconomics. TA. Undergrad. level. AY 2003.

Universidad del Norte Santo Tomás de Aquino (Argentina)

o Mathematics. Main Instructor. Undergrad. level. Spring 2006.

#### Personal

Languages English (proficient), Spanish (native speaker).

Nationality Argentine Citizenship, Canadian Permanent Resident, U.S. O1 Visa holder.

Marital Stat. Married.

#### References

- Prof. Enrique G. Mendoza. UPenn. egme@sas.upenn.edu
- o Dr. Pablo N. D'Erasmo. FRB Philadelphia. pabloderasmo@gmail.com
- Or. Leonardo Martinez. IMF Institute. lmartinez4@imf.org
- Prof. Carmen M. Reinhart. Harvard. carmen\_reinhart@harvard.edu